On the border between France and
Switzerland is the biggest science
experiment ever built. It's this huge
tunnel, over 100 m underground and 27 km
long. And inside that tunnel, scientists
put a long blue tube, and inside that
tube they put two pipes that they keep
colder and emptier than outer space. And
down those pipes, they fire particles
smaller than atoms in opposite
directions, pushing them faster and
faster and faster until, when they're
almost at the speed of light, they smash
together. But my question was, how do
they get them to actually hit each
other? It's like shooting grains of salt
at each other from insanely far away.
Seriously, think about this. How would
you do that? If you just thought fire
tons of salt, that's exactly what they
do. They don't just fire 100 or 1,000
protons at each other. They fire 100
billion. And when they do that, 100
billion versus 100 billion, guess how
many actually collide? 60. Six zero.
Which is why they do the whole thing
over and over and over again, 30 million
times per second. If you want to know
more, watch our longer episode or just
follow here for more videos.